Guide to the Becca Albee Riot Grrrl Papers ca. 1992-1996 MSS.273
Fales Library and Special Collections
Becca Albee Riot Grrrl Collection
ca. 1992-1996
Fales Library and Special Collections
Albee, Becca
MSS.273
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Becca Albee is a musician, writer, and visual artist who was active in the early days of the Riot Grrrl movement in Olympia, Washington. This collection is comprised of materials--including original lyric sheets and artwork, posters, photos, and fan mail--pertaining to Ms. Albee's involvement with the bands Excuse 17 and Heartless Martin, as well as a small number of personal papers, ephemera and objects.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged primarily by topic, much as they were received. The collection was processed at the folder level and loose items were given preservation attention as needed.
See the Scope and Content Notes for more specific details about each series.
Scope and Content
The Becca Albee Riot Grrrl Collection contains materials that document Albee's involvement in the Riot Grrrl-inspired bands Excuse 17 and Heartless Martin. Also included are personal papers and objects related to Albee's visual art and writing. The bulk of the materials are from 1993-1995.
The collection is divided into four series:
Series I: Music: This series is comprised of materials directly related to Becca Albee's musical career including original lyric sheets, fan mail, gig posters, album artwork, and photography.
Subseries A: Excuse 17
Subseries B: Heartless Martin
Series II: Personal: This series contains documentation of Becca Albee's personal work not related to bands including visual art, Riot Grrrl zines, and a series of notepads with messages from Becca and her friends.
Subseries A: Visual Art
Subseries B: Zines
Subseries C: Miscellaneous Papers and Objects
Series III: Media: This series has visual and audio recordings of work by Excuse 17, Lync, Heavens to Betsy as well as film footage taken by Becca Albee.
Subseries A: Access Copies (currently no access copies exist for this collection)
Subseries B: Originals
Oversize Series I: Includes materials too large to be stored in a records carton or photo binder.
Subseries A: Excuse 17
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Related Materials
Tammy Rae Carland Riot Grrrl Papers (unprocessed)
Robert Blanchon Papers and Collection
Biographical Note
Becca Albee was involved in the Riot Grrrl movement in the early 1990's in Olympia, Washington. She was a participant in many early Riot Grrrl meetings, collaborated on Riot Grrrl zines, and was a member of two important bands of the time, Excuse 17 and Heartless Martin. These bands, along with others like Bikini Kill and Bratmobile, contributed to the feminist, activist, DIY culture that was evolving in Olympia at the time.
Founded in 1993, Excuse 17 was comprised of Becca Albee, Carrie Brownstein, and CJ Phillips. The band released two full-length albums: Excuse 17 (1994, Chainsaw Records) and Some Friends Are Dangerous (1995, Kill Rock Stars). They also released a split 7" with Lync on Candy-Ass Records. Also in 1993, Becca Albee teamed up with Corin Tucker to form a one-off collaboration called Heartless Martin, releasing a cassette on Chainsaw Records.
Albee graduated from the Evergreen State College in 1995. She earned her MFA at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, where she studied with Tammy Rae Carland and Robert Blanchon. Currently, Albee is an Assistant Professor of Art teaching photography in the Art Department and Electronic Design and Multimedia Program at The City College of New York, CUNY. She lives in Brooklyn and is an active visual artist.
Sources:
Lower Manhattan Cultural Council
All Music Guide
Chainsaw Records
Kill Rock Stars
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The digital access copies in the collection were created by the Barbara Goldsmith Preservation and Conservation Department. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact nyuspecialcollections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Excuse 17 (Musical group); Videocassettes.; Lyric sheets.; Audiocassettes.; Photographs.; Musicians -- 1990-2000; Fliers (printed matter); Photographers -- United States.; Correspondence.; Rock music -- United States -- 1991-2000; Feminism and art.; Zines.; Riot grrrl movement.; Corin, Tucker; C.J., Phillips; Carrie, Brownstein
- Series I: Music, 191667
  - Subseries A: Excuse 17, 191668
    - Original Artwork and Photos, undated; 191669 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Posters and Flyers, undated; 191670 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Administrative and Press Releases, 191671 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 191672 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Set Lists and Lyrics, undated; 191673 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Heartless Martin, 191674
    - Artwork and Documentation, undated; 191675 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Personal, 191676
  - Subseries A: Visual Art, 191677
    - Photos, Press Releases, and Compact, undated; 191678 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Zines, 191679
    - Riot Grrrl zines, undated; 191680 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Abstract
      What is Riot Grrrl Anyway? [Olympia] [no. 4]
      This mini-zine compiles a number of writers' thinking on what riot grrrl means, and emphasizes personal relationships to the movement and reasons for joining or identifying with it. Descriptions are made in relation to sexual abuse in families and relationships, the general oppressiveness of fathers and men, the power of female collectivization, female criticism of riot grrrl, and the domination of men in society and punk. Anecdotes of riot grrrl meeting experiences are abundant. Contains an excerpt from Riot Grrrl D.C. zine on the freeform nature of riot grrrl, as well as a list of names and addresses of fellow riot grrrl publications.
      Riot Grrrl: Huh? [Olympia]
      This zine begins with an essay concerning the reductive impact of negative views and perceived exclusion as responses to collective action, especially as this relates to riot grrrl. A critique piece and collage on male-imposed standards of beauty follows. An extended excerpt from Peace and Freedom on the interlocking aspects of male, white, and straight privilege and the importance of its perpetrators recognizing this oppression is included. Anti-police rhetoric and the desire for self-policing and social control follows in a subsequent piece. Later pieces question male dominance and the impairment of pro-choice goals in the Rock for Choice organization, anti-union attitudes in local workplaces, and tensions created through physical aggression at live music shows.
  - Subseries C: Miscellaneous Papers and Objects, 191681
    - Door Notepads [1 of 2] NO DUPLICATION, undated; 191682 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      General
      No duplication of the door notepads is allowed
    - Door Notepads [2 of 2] NO DUPLICATION, 191683 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Resume, Rent Receipts, and To-Do List, 1992-1996; 191684 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Papers and Items from bowling bag, undated; 191685 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Blue and white bowling bag, undated; 191686 (Box 4, Object ID: 273.2.0001)
- Series III: Media, 191687
  - Subseries A: Access Copies, 202297
    - She was Horrid, 1994 (Box Digitized Access Files, File 273.0001)
      Scope and Contents
      A short film directed by Becca Albee and Sarah Kennedy, music by Carrie Brownstein.
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Format: MP4, Duration: 10 min., Source: 273.001 [16mm film]
      Conditions Governing Access
      Patrons are not allowed to photograph the film while viewing in the reading room.
    - Excuse 17 Live, 1994; 273.0003 (Box Digitized Access Files, File 273.0003)
      Format: MP4, Duration: 15 min., Source: 273.0003 [VHS]
      Additional Label Information
      [Excuse 17--8-5-94--CBGB] [Bikini Kill--10-31-94--CBGB] [Nilla--12-1-94--UnderAcme] [Tryke--Softies]
      [Nilla-2494 Loft Ave. Baldwin, NY]
    - E17 Practice, undated; 273.0004 (Box Digitized Access Files, File 273.0004)
      Format: MP4, Duration: 31 min., Source: 273.0004 [1/8" audiocassette]
    - Excuse 17 LIVE at (under) Spa Studio, 1995-05-22; 273.0009 (Box Digitized Access Files, File 273.0009)
      Format: MP4, Duration: 27 min, Source: 273.0009 [1/8" audiocassette]
  - Subseries B: Originals, 191688
    - ["She Was Horrid"] [Release Print] [360'] [B/W Print], 1994; 273.001; 191689 (Film 273.001)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      Format: 16mm film, Black and White, 24 fps, Duration: 10 min.
      Currently available. See Subseries A: Access Copies
    - Excuse 17/Lync Split 7" Youth on Fire, 1994; 191690 (Box 2, Disc ID: 273.0002)
      7" vinyl sound disc with paper sleeve and original artwork
    - Excuse 17 Live, 1994; 273.0003; 191691 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0003)
      Format: VHS, Duration: 15 min.
    - E17 Practice, undated; 191782 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0004)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements Note
      Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 31 min.
    - Excuse Seventeen 1/95 1st Mix, 1995; 191783 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0005)
      100 minute audio cassette in case.
    - Excuse Seventeen 1/95 Second Mix, 1995; 191784 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0006)
      60 minute audio cassette in case.
    - Excuse Seventeen demo, 1993; 191785 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0007)
      Audio cassette in case with original artwork & inserts.
    - Lync & Heavens to Betsy on the Radio/Color Outside the Lines, undated; 191786 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0008)
      90 minute audio cassette in case.
    - Excuse 17 LIVE at (under) Spa Studio 5/22/95, 1995; 191787 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0009)
      60 minute audio cassette in case with insert.
    - Excuse Seventeen Live at Yoyo a Gogo, undated; 191788 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0010)
      Audio cassette in case.
    - active agent equals anything, undated; 191789 (Box 2, Cassette ID: 273.0011)
      Audio cassette in case with original artwork.
- Oversize Series I: Music, 191977
  - Subseries A: Excuse 17, 191978
    - Original Artwork and Photos, 1993, undated; 191979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Posters and Flyers, 1994, undated; 191980 (Box 3, Folder 2)